Avinash Ramesh

San Jose, CA | (408) 338-5862 | avinashramesh2312@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/avinash94/ | Github: github.com/rameshavinash94/

SUMMARY

I am a skilled software professional with nearly 6 years of experience in the backend engineering, specializing in data-driven design, OOAD patterns (*strategy, singleton, factory, builder, chain of responsibility, observer, dependency injection,*), REST APIs, relational databases, data pipeline design, warehouse modeling(*Dimensional/ Datavault*), and workflow automation.

EDUCATION

San José State University San Jose, CA, USA

Master of Science in Computer Software Engineering (Specializing in Data science)

August 2021 - May 2023

Courses: Enterprise Software Systems, Data Mining, Advanced Data Mining, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Software Systems Engineering, Special topics in ML and Reinforcement Learning. GPA:3.9/4

Anna University Chennai, TN, INDIA Bachelor of Technology in Information Technology

June 2012 - April 2016

EXPERIENCE

Carl Zeiss Meditec, Dublin, CA

May 2022 - December 2022

Software Engineer Internship - Building fullstack big data product for clinical analysis

- Spearheaded the entire product development lifecycle for **three** key functionalities of CRUD-based DICOM application: uploading series of scans, annotating studies, comprehensive metadata search and exporting dicom metadata & scans.
- Designed frontend using React, built event-driven data pipelines using Azure services (*ADF, Azure Batch, and Azure Databricks*), developed scalable REST APIs (*Fastapi, ORM-SQLAlchemy*) handling nearly **hundreds of concurrent users**, performed API pagination, deployed database models (*PostgreSQL*), and created an internal cache store.
- Follow object oriented design patterns(*strategy*, *singleton*, *factory*) & dependency ingestion techniques to develop loosely coupled applications.
- Collaborated with managers and downstream users to plan, design and develop an internal data product to fasten clinical research and analytics for AI teams.

ITI DATA, Chennai, India

Associate - Software Engineering / Data Engineering (Big Data Platforms)

July 2019 - July 2021

- Planned infrastructure to process internal & external vendor data feeds for global use within Citigroup and apply business rules & data selection hierarchy on individual data attribute levels to create a golden data source.
- Write automation scripts using python/unix shell script for data validation and processing tasks to reduce man hours.
- Created Hive tables with partitioning and bucketing for efficient data access; deployed spark pipelines; optimized existing SQL queries by 30%; and wrote Sqoop jobs to import, export, and update data between HDFS, Hive, and relational databases.
- Migrated existing data pipelines(*Abinitio*) to Spark distributed framework (POC & productionize pipelines) nearly **40%** faster thereby reducing licensing costs spent on ETL tools.
- Automated ETL pipelines across millions of rows using Autosys scheduler reducing manual workloads.
- Identified, reviewed, and implemented internal process improvements: automating manual processes, optimizing data delivery by 50%, re-designing infrastructure for greater scalability, etc.

Analyst - Software Engineering / Data Engineering

August 2016 - June 2019

- Designed data marts and written REST API endpoints for handling various data extraction and querying tasks for BI engineering to interact with databases to design dashboards, and perform real-time data analysis.
- Architectured ETL pipelines to extract more than **2 million** records on a weekly basis from various vendors(Reuters, Bloomberg, etc.), wrangle ingested data, apply business transformation rules, and load into desired formats.
- Created a framework to recognize **data anomalies** and produce daily automated reports to reduce turnaround time to nearly **half** for addressing data problems.
- Designed db models and applied **Slowly Changing Dimensions(SCD)** in Data Warehouse to track historic changes.
- Remodeled functional logic of python similarity script using Numba jit, numpy arrays and map operations resulting in decrease in time complexity by nearly 3/4th.

SKILLS

Programming languages: Python, Unix Shell Scripting, SQL, Java, Javascript **Big Data Frameworks/Tools**: Spark, Hive, Hadoop, HDFS, YARN, Sqoop

Web Frameworks/API: HTML, CSS, React, Flask, Fastapi

Data Formats: CSV, JSON, Parquet, Avro, DICOM

ML Libraries: Numpy, Pandas, Matplotlib, Pyspark, Spacy, Scikit-learn, Keras, Tensorflow, Pytorch

Orchestration & ETL: Autosys, Crontab, Airflow, Ab Initio, OpenRefine, ADF

Databases: Oracle 11g & 12c, SQLite, HBase, Postgresql, Redis

Visualization: Tableau, Microsoft Excel, Streamlit

CI/CD tools: IBM UrbanCode Deploy, AWS code pipeline, Azure Devops

Container Technology & Management, Configuration: Docker, Kubernetes, Ansible